<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Reasons for non-conformity examined and refuted, in answer to a late Letter from a minister to a person of quality, shewing some reasons for his non-conformity.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R497cA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8497</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12529920</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12529920</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27954)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 304:4 or 2015:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Reasons for non-conformity examined and refuted, in answer to a late Letter from a minister to a person of quality, shewing some reasons for his non-conformity.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby, at the Bishop's Head in St. Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Letter from a minister" is written by A.B. Cf. p. 3.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 304:4 identified as Wing B26 (number cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York and Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>A. B., --  Minister. --  Letter from a minister to a person of quality, shewing some reasons for his non-conformity.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62754:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REASONS FOR <hi>Non-conformity</hi> EXAMINED and REFUTED, IN ANSWER To a Late LETTER from a MINISTER TO A <hi>PERSON</hi> of <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALITY, SHEWING</hi> Some <hi>Reaſons</hi> for his <hi>Non-conformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s Head in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:62754:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62754:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO A LETTER from a MINISTER TO A <hi>PERSON</hi> of <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALITY, SHEWING</hi> Some <hi>Reaſons</hi> for his Non-conformity.</head>
            <p>BEING lately in a Bookſeller's Shop with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to gratifie my curioſity in peruſing ſome of thoſe many Pamphlets, which either a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken or factious zeal crowds into the World, I met with a Letter pretended to be writ from a <hi>Miniſter</hi> to a Perſon of Quality, ſhewing ſome <hi>Reaſons</hi> of his Non-conformity. I have often obſerved this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in ſome mean but vain people, who dare not look upon Perſons of Quality, when they are preſent, to talk of them with great familiarity, as their peculiar Intimates and Confidents; an Art, whereby both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Fanaticks think to conciliate great reverence to themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62754:3"/>
            <p>However I was very glad to ſee this Pamphlet, which being a ſingle ſheet, was quickly read, and if it were thought requiſite, as quickly anſwered, and indeed I expected either ſome new reaſons of Non-conformity, or ſome new ſtrength given to their old reaſons; but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a peruſal of it ſoon diſcovered my miſtake, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently concluded, that ſuch ſtuff as this could not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to ſatisfie a Perſon of Quality, but to impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Injudicious Rabble, and that we muſt expect a new Letter of Reaſons for Non conformity every week or fortnight, like the <hi>Domeſtick Intelligence,</hi> or Poor <hi>Robin:</hi> a way, which has been found very effectual to corrupt the minds of weak and unſtable People. For which reaſon (though my other occaſions would ſufficiently have pleaded my excuſe) I reſolved in great charity to undertake this Gentleman, either to ſatisfie him, if he be an honeſt and Impartial Inquirer, or to uſe as great diligence to undeceive People, as he does to deceive them.</p>
            <p>To let paſs his Introduction, which I confeſs I can neither make Grammar nor Senſe of, he tells us, that <q rend="inline">three grand Declarations are required to be made by all thoſe who will conform: The Firſt concerning the Book of Common-Prayer, the ſecond concerning taking up Arms againſt the King, the third concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Solemn League and Covenant. Now with reference to all theſe (eſpecially the firſt and laſt) I have had hitherto inſuperable objections againſt the making any ſuch Declaration.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I am heartily ſorry, that any Men retain theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and more that they dare to own them, and yet there were no great hurt in this, would but our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours take the alarm, and conſider what Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence is fit to be allowed thoſe Men, who profeſs, that they have inſuperable objections againſt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62754:3"/> Treaſon and Rebellion to be a ſin, and that they dare not renounce that Covenant, which involved this Nation in a Bloudy War, which pull'd down Church and State, and ended in the Barbarous Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the beſt of Kings: for thoſe who believe they are ſtill under the obligation of that Covenant, muſt neceſſarily believe, that they are ſtill bound to act over the ſame Villanies, when they ſhall have power to do it. But of this more, when our Author ſhall think fit to give us his objections againſt the two laſt Declarations, at preſent we are only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to vindicate the Firſt, the Declaration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Book of Common-Prayer.</p>
            <p>And his great objection againſt this is a great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, or a diſingenuous perverting the ſenſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Declaration: The words are theſe. I A. B. <hi>do declare my unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in and by the Book,</hi> entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <note place="margin">B. L.</note> 
               <hi>The Book of Common-Prayer, &amp;c.</hi> Upon which words, he thus comments, <hi>Surely words could not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by all the wit of man more comprehenſive and more ſignificant to teſtifie our higheſt juſtification and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every point and ſyllable, of every rite and ceremony, of every matter and thing contained in the whole Book, and in every page and line of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This he deſcants on at large and greatly triumphs in the unreaſonableneſs and abſurdity of ſuch a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and I confeſs, I am perfectly of his mind, and would be a Non-conformiſt to any Church in the World, that ſhould require ſuch a declaration from me: but then thoſe very Arguments, whereby he proves the unreaſonableneſs of ſuch a declaration, do abundantly convince me, that this is not the ſenſe and meaning of the declaration: And every man muſt be of my mind, who will but think ſo charitably of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62754:4"/> his Prince and Parliament and the Convocation, as not to believe them to be all mad.</p>
            <p>For would any men in their wits, who deny the Infallibility of Pope and Councils, (as he well obſerves the Church of <hi>England</hi> does) require ſuch an aſſent to any book of humane compoſition, as ſhall ſuppoſe it to be infallible: for ſo this declaration (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that latitude of ſenſe he beſtows on it) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, that there is not the leaſt poſſible miſtake in the whole Book of Common-prayer, but that it is as infallible as the Bible, nay more infallible than any Copy of the Bible now extant in the World in any Language, in which there may be ſome poſſible mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes through the fault of the Tranſlators or Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers, as he obſerves, and as was before obſerved in the very Preface to the Common-Prayer-Book, that <hi>in common equity there muſt be allowed a juſt and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable conſtruction to all humane Writings, eſpecially ſuch as are ſet forth by Authority, and even to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beſt Tranſlations of the Holy Scripture it ſelf:</hi> which is a plain Argument, that they never deſigned ſuch a declaration of Aſſent to the Book of Common-Prayer, as excludes all poſſible miſtakes, and gives us a general rule not to expound Acts of Parliament, or Publick Declarations, (which are <hi>humane wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings ſet forth by Authority</hi>) to an abſurd or impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſenſe. In like manner Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in her Injunctions brands thoſe for <hi>malicious Perſons,</hi> who put ſuch <hi>perverſe conſtructions</hi> on the Oaths of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, as could not <hi>by any equity of words, or good ſenſe be thereof gathered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet upon this miſtake our Author proceeds to ſhow the difference between old and new Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and aſſerts, that <hi>ever ſince our happy reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Miniſters were not ſo ſtrictly enjoyned to declare
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62754:4"/> their unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in and by the Book;</hi> but it was <hi>only appointed to be read and uſed, and the Rites and Ceremonies of it duly to be obſerved:</hi> which he calls their <hi>moderation</hi> and <hi>piety,</hi> very good words, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed too good not to be qualified and recalled, and therefore adds, <hi>at leaſt their prudence and policy:</hi> for he ſuppoſes, <q rend="inline">that a great many hundreds, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in thoſe days, would not have conformed, had any ſuch declaration been required of them; and upon this account doubts not to declare, that preſent conformity is foreign and quite of another nature from conformity heretofore; conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now much more forced and violated by them in the Chair:</q> which is ſaid to vindicate themſelves for diſſenting ſo much from many ancient Puritans, who though they diſliked many things, yet conformed and peaceably ſubmitted to publick Conſtitutions.</p>
            <p>But this Perſon is either a great ſtranger to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſince the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or cannot but know, that if there were no ſuch publick declaration, yet there were publick ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required of the conforming Clergy, which is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to a declaration; for he muſt be a man of a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſqueamiſh conſcience, who will not declare that which he can and does ſubſcribe. For what he aſſerts, that there was no more required formerly of the Clergy, but barely to uſe and ſubmit to the Common-prayer and the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church, is notoriouſly falſe. In the Articles publiſhed by the Authority of King <hi>Edw. VI.</hi> this is one, <q rend="inline">The Book, which of late time was given to the Church of <hi>England</hi> by the Kings <note place="margin">B. L.</note> Authority and the Parliament, containing the manner and form of praying and miniſtring the Sacraments in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> likewiſe alſo the Book of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62754:5"/> ordering Miniſters of the Church, ſet forth by the ſame Authority are godly, and in no point repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the wholeſome Doctrine of the Goſpel, but agreeable thereunto, furthering and beautifying the ſame not a little, and therefore of all faithful members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and chiefly of the Miniſters of the Word, they ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and allowed with all readineſs of mind and thankſgiving, and to be commended to the People of God: which as you ſhall hear more preſently</q> is not inferiour to an <hi>unfeigned aſſent and conſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Article indeed is left out of thoſe, which were ſet forth by the Authority of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> but inſtead of it, the Clergy were required to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe this promiſe or declaration. <q rend="inline">I ſhall read the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>B. L.</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements by the <hi>Queen.</hi>
                  </note> Service appointed, plainly, diſtinctly and audibly, that all the People may hear and underſtand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In the Reign and by the Authority of King <hi>James</hi> were publiſhed the Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, which are of force in the Church of <hi>England</hi> to this day: and it is ſufficiently known, that by the <hi>36 Canon,</hi> every Perſon to be ordained or promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any Eccleſiaſtical Benefice, or Function, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſubſcribe the Three Articles, the ſecond of which concerns the Book of Common-prayer, and of ordaining and conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, that it contains nothing in it contrary to the Word of God, and may be lawfully uſed, and that he himſelf will uſe that ſame form, and no other: from whence it appears, that there was ſomething more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of conforming Miniſters in thoſe days, than only to read the Book of Common-prayer, and to obſerve the Rites and Ceremonies of it, as this Author ignorantly aſſerts, for they were alſo required by ſubſcription to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62754:5"/> their approbation of it, as fit to be uſed, and their promiſe, that they would uſe it.</p>
            <p>But ſtill, they were not <hi>ſo ſtrictly injoyned to declare their unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in and by the Book.</hi> Right, not in theſe very words, but to the ſame ſenſe: for to own, that there is nothing in the Common prayer Book, which is contrary to the Word of God, and that it may be lawfully uſed, and that we will uſe it, is equivalent to an unfeigned aſſent, and conſent. No ſays our Author, for <hi>Aſſent with reference to the party aſſenting relates to his underſtanding; and with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the thing aſſented to, it relates to the truth and rightfulneſs of it:</hi> So again, <hi>Conſent with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the party conſenting, relates to his will; and with reference to the thing conſented to, it relates to that goodneſs, expediency, behovefulneſs of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A very wiſe and grave obſervation, as if I could not aſſent to the doing of what is to be done, as well as to the truth of a propoſition, or could not aſſent to the lawfulneſs of a thing, without aſſenting to it as every way fitteſt and beſt and moſt expedient; as if I could not conſent to ſubmit to the uſe of what is lawful and legally impoſed, without <hi>chuſing every thing mentioned and preſcribed in the ſame Book, as moſt eligible and behoveful to be done, practiſed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,</hi> as this Author is pleaſed to paraphraſe <hi>an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeigned Conſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſatisfie this Gentleman in the ſignification of theſe words <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> it may be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to give him Qu. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s interpretation of them, in the Preface to the Articles, <hi>An.</hi> 1504. <q rend="inline">Whereupon by diligent conference and communication, and at laſt <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Sparrow</hi>'s Collection.</note> by <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> of the Perſons before-ſaid, theſe orders and rules enſuing have been thought meet and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62754:6"/> convenient to be uſed and followed; not yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing theſe rules as laws equivalent with the eternal Word of God, and as of neceſſity to bind the conſciences of her ſubjects in the nature of them conſidered in themſelves—but as temporal orders meer Eccleſiaſtical, without any vain ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and as rules in ſome part of Diſcipline concerning decency, diſtinction and order for the time.</q> So that the Queen, and the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the other Biſhops in commiſſion with him, who drew up thoſe Articles, thought we might give our aſſent and conſent to orders and rules (and by the ſame reaſon to a Book of Common-prayer) as <hi>only meet and convenient to be uſed and followed;</hi> and that we may give ſuch an <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary rules, which are alterable at pleaſure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ſuppoſed to be every way perfect, or not to have the leaſt error or defect in them.</p>
            <p>And in this ſenſe the Act of Uniformity requires our unfeigned aſſent and conſent to the Book of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayer, &amp;c. that is to the uſe of it, as is expreſly mentioned immediately before this declaration: that every Miniſter ſhall <hi>openly and publickly before the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation declare his unfeigned aſſent and conſent to the uſe of all things in the ſaid Book contained and preſcribed, in theſe words and no other.</hi> I <hi>A. B. do here declare,</hi> &amp;c. Now when the Act it ſelf limits the ſignification of theſe words, Aſſent and Conſent, only to the uſe, it evidently betrays a perverſe and malicious deſign, to affix ſuch a large ſignification on them, without the leaſt appearance of reaſon, as to render that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration very abſurd and impious, or at beſt very ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious to honeſt men.</p>
            <p>As for what he urges, that the Act it ſelf expounds <hi>conſent</hi> by <hi>approve,</hi> where it is ſaid of a Lecturer, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62754:6"/> 
               <hi>he ſhall give his aſſent to, and approbation of the ſaid Book, and to the uſe of all the prayers, &amp;c.</hi> I would fain know how it can be otherwiſe; for he, who aſſents and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, muſt approve, as far as he aſſents and conſents, but why cannot we approve of the uſe of a Book, or approve of a Book, as lawful to be uſed, as well as aſſent and conſent to the uſe of it? ſo that what our Author ſeems ſo paſſionately to wiſh, <hi>that they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Falkner</hi>'s <hi>Libertas Eccleſ.</hi> c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>no more in conformity than uſe and ſubmiſſion,</hi> is indeed all, that is required of the conforming Cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gy, and is all, that is neceſſary to be required to attain the end of that Act, which was to eſtabliſh uniformity in worſhip, that <hi>there may be an univerſal agreement in the publick worſhip of Almighty God, and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that every perſon in this Realm may certainly know the rule to which he is to conform in Publick Worſhip;</hi> which are the very words of the Act: but it has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been the practice of theſe men, to force another ſenſe upon the words of Oaths and publick declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than was ever intended by our Governours, on purpoſe to juſtifie their unjuſt clamours, and to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Schiſm and Faction.</p>
            <p>Having thus in general juſtified the declaration of unfeigned aſſent and conſent, it is time to conſider his particular exceptions againſt the Book of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayer: And his Firſt exception is againſt reading <hi>the Apocrypha as Leſſons for the day:</hi> but he ought to have ſaid, for what day; for there is not one Leſſon out of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> appointed for any Sunday throughout the year; and is it not great impudence in theſe men to reproach the Church of <hi>England</hi> for appointing the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrypha</hi> to be read ſometimes on the Week-days, who take no care themſelves, that either the Holy Scriptures or <hi>Apocrypha</hi> ſhould be read in their Conventicles all the week, nor ſcarce on Sundays; eſpecially conſidering,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62754:7"/> that there is always one Leſſon out of the Canonical Scripture appointed to be read, beſides the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> and I ſuppoſe they will not aſſert it abſolutely neceſſary every time we meet to worſhip God, to read two Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Holy Scriptures; for they themſelves very ſeldom read one on their weekly Lectures, whatever they do on Sundays: we pay much greater reverence to the holy Scriptures than our Accuſers do, as never meeting together for the worſhip of God without read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome portion of them; what is our fault then? not a neglect to read the Scriptures, but that ſometimes we read ſome part of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> together with the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; and if this be all, it is no other fault, than what <note place="margin">See <hi>Falkners libertas Eccl. ch. 4. ſect. 5.</hi>
               </note> the ancienteſt and pureſt Churches have been guilty of: as is well known to thoſe, who are acquainted with the Hiſtory of the Chriſtian Church, and there are few Proteſtant Writers of any note, but have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, or at leaſt allowed the reading of them. But they are <hi>fabulous Legends,</hi> ſuch as <hi>of Tobit and his Dog, Bel and the Dragon, Judith and Baruch:</hi> I ſuppoſe this Author does not know, that the 5 Ch. of <hi>Tobit</hi> is left out of our Kalendar, nor that many of the ancient Fathers did believe theſe to be true ſtories, though he is pleaſed confidently to call them fabulous Legends, I never ſaw any arguments yet to prove them Fables, but what would admit of a very fair ſolution, when this Author produces any, I ſhall conſider them: But ſuppoſing them to be fables, that is parabolical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, they are never the leſs fit for that to be read in Chriſtian Aſſemblies, ſince they may ſerve for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, or comfort, or reproof, as the Parables of our Saviour do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But they are read under the notion of Holy Scripture, for ſo in the whole lump together they are ſtiled in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, no note of diſcrimination to make any diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62754:7"/> one and the other:</hi> and has this Author then the impudence to charge the Church of <hi>England</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no diſtinction between the Canonical Scripture and the <hi>Apocrypha?</hi> if not, is it not done like a very good Chriſtian, ſliely to inſinuate ſo foul an imputation as this? if he does think the Church guilty, let him tell me the meaning of the ſixth Article of Religion, wherein our Church declares, <hi>In the name of the Holy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">B. L.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture, we do underſtand thoſe Canonical Books, of whoſe authority was never any doubt in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">And the other Books (as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith) the Church <note place="margin">B. L.</note> doth read for example of life and inſtitution of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but yet doth not apply them to eſtabliſh any doctrine.</q> How is it poſſible for the beſt Church in the World to eſcape the envenomed Tongues and Pens of theſe Men, who do not bluſh to charge her with ſuch doctrines, as are directly contrary to her own Articles? Had it not been more reaſonable to aſſert, that the order takes no notice of the Apocryphal Leſſons, than that it includes the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> in the common title of <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> which is the plain truth, for it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentions the Leſſons out of the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reckoning the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> ſo well known, and ſo plainly diſcovered by the Kalendar, when it was once underſtood, that there was no need of particular directions about it.</p>
            <p>There is one objection more with reference to the Kalendar, that <hi>ſome Books of the Sacred Canon are wholly left out, and never to be read, ſome of them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a very little, ſome of them but half to be read, and many of them mutilated and curtailed as to ſeveral cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pters contained in them.</hi> Now to ſhow you of what force this objection is, let us firſt conſider how much of the Holy Scripture is appointed to be read every Year by our Church: The Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62754:8"/> read over every Month, the moſt part of the old Teſtament once a Year, the new Teſtament except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Revelations</hi> thrice every Year, beſides Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Goſpels: And have not theſe Men great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to find fault with our Kalendar, who don't read the tenth part of the Bible once a Year in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles?</p>
            <p>Secondly, the deſign of publick reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is for publick inſtruction, and therefore the Church may very prudently leave out ſuch parts of Scripture, as are dark and obſcure, and not eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood without an Expoſitor, or have not ſuch an immediate influence upon the government of our lives, and reſerve them to be read by Chriſtians at home, or to be expounded to the People by publick Teachers: and ſuch for the moſt part are thoſe omiſſions, which this Author complains of; dark and obſcure Prophecies or Genealogies, or ſuch Hiſtories, as are related in ſome other Books, which are appointed to be read.</p>
            <p>And now Thirdly, I would deſire this Gentleman to prove, that it is abſolutely neceſſary to read the whole Scripture in our Churches; if it be, let our Diſſenters firſt correct themſelves, before they cenſure thoſe, who are more juſt and innocent; if it be not, then it is no fault to omit ſome parts of Scripture, which are leaſt fitted to the edification of a promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuous multitude, while nothing is omitted, which is neceſſary to their inſtruction in Faith and manners: and when he ſhows any ſuch omiſſion, I will refuſe to conform too.</p>
            <p>To conclude this argument, it is well obſerved by <note place="margin">Falkners libertas Eccl. ch. 4. ſ. 5.</note> a Learned man, that <q rend="inline">the ancient <hi>Jews,</hi> who divided the old Teſtament into the Law, the Prophets, and the Hagiographa, did for a long time only read the Law in the Synagogues, after which only a Section of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62754:8"/> Prophets was added; but that the Hagiographa (which included all the Books from the beginning of the Chronicles to the end of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> beſides <hi>Ruth, Lamentations</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi>) were not read in the Synagogues, hath been obſerv'd from the <hi>Talmudiſts:</hi> and this is agreeable to divers paſſages of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, <hi>Luk. 4. 16. Acts 13. 15, 27. Act.</hi> 15. 21. yet Chriſt and his Apoſtles blamed not the <hi>Jews,</hi> but joyned with them in this Service.</q> Such a vaſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is there between the temper of our Lord and his Apoſtles, and our Phariſaical Schiſmaticks.</p>
            <p>His next objection is againſt <hi>the order appointed for the Miniſtration of Baptiſm,</hi> which is divided into three Branches.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that <hi>he does not approve of the ſtrict requiring of God-fathers and God-mothers to ſtand as Sureties and Undertakers for the Child to be baptized,</hi> viz. <hi>that he ſhall renounce the Devil and all his works, and conſtantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve God's holy Word, and obediently keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> His objection is againſt the <hi>ſtrict</hi> requiring of this, and yet it is not ſo <hi>ſtrictly</hi> required, as to make it eſſential to the nature of Baptiſm, as is evident in private Baptiſm, which is declared valid without it: but let us hear his Reaſons againſt this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that <hi>it is unſcriptural:</hi> but it is not contrary to Scripture, and that is anſwer enough, till he can prove, that the Church has no power to appoint any Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies or obſervances, but what are expreſly warranted by Scripture, eſpecially this being an ancient practice both in the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Church; and as the <hi>Leyden</hi> Profeſſors think (Perſons whom I know our <note place="margin">Synop pur. Theol. diſp. 44. n. 54.</note> Author reverences) countenanced by Scripture alſo, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8. 2, 3. as has been before obſerved by Mr. <hi>Falkner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſecond objection againſt God-fathers, is, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62754:9"/> 
               <hi>the Father of the Child is left out, if not wholly thruſt out;</hi> a great fault this, but how does he prove it? becauſe, <hi>he is not mentioned, nor taken notice of at all, in that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſtipulation, as if he had no concern in it:</hi> a very wiſe argument! I borrow a Hundred Pounds, two of my Friends are bound for the payment of it, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any farther notice of me, than that the Money was lent to me, <hi>Ergo,</hi> I am diſcharged of this debt, becauſe other Perſons have given a Bond for it, and I have given none: The obligation of Parents to edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Children is founded on the Laws of Nature and Religion, and acknowledged by all Mankind with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an explicite ſtipulation; the obligation of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers is voluntary, and therefore requires an expreſs promiſe, and is deſigned as an additional ſecurity to the Church for the religious education of Children baptized.</p>
            <p>His third objection is, that God-fathers do not keep this promiſe, but involve themſelves in the guilt of <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>perjury:</hi> this I muſt acknowledge to be a great fault, and I fear too many are chargeable with it; but this is the fault of the Men, not of the Conſtitution: it is a demonſtration of great prudence and piety in the Church, by all poſſible ways to ſecure the vertuous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of Children, who are baptized in their infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that the Church may not hereafter be ſcandalized with the ignorance and vices of ſuch untaught and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſciplined Chriſtians: the preſumption of a religious education is neceſſary to give any Child a right to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, and therefore it is very commendable in the Church to take collateral ſecurity, where it may be had, as well as the direct ſecurity of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: Did our Church exact any promiſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement from God fathers, which could not be kept, ſhe might be charged with the guilt of their <hi>lying</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62754:9"/> 
               <hi>perjury,</hi> as he calls it; but when the promiſe may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be performed, and is nothing but what one Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Friend ought to do for another, when occaſion requires, without ſuch a promiſe, let every Man bear the guilt of his neglect, without reproaching the moſt prudent and wholeſome Conſtitutions.</p>
            <p>His ſecond exception againſt the order of Baptiſm, is againſt the uſe of the ſign of the Croſs, but his objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt this are ſo very trifling, that they will give an anſwerer no great trouble: he knows not how to underſtand thoſe words <hi>in token,</hi> when the Child is ſigned with the ſign of the Croſs, <hi>in token that he ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſs the faith of Chriſt crucified:</hi> why, what difficulty is there in underſtanding this word <hi>token,</hi> which is a plain Engliſh word, and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly underſtood by plain Engliſh-men? but if he wants a comment, he may take Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi>'s, that <hi>it is a declarative token of duty, which afterwards the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Defence of three Cerem.</note> 
               <hi>perſon ought to perform, &amp;c.</hi> but <hi>he believes the generality may miſtake in token,</hi> for <hi>in vertue and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of this ſign:</hi> but I believe, he ſuſpects the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality to be more ſilly than they are, till their underſtandings are debauched with fanaticiſm, and I need not tell him, who may be thanked for that: but the way of theſe Men is to put ſcruples and whimſies into Peoples heads, and then to cry down the moſt innocent and ſober uſages, for fear of giving <hi>an occaſion of miſunderſtanding to the vulgar and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious:</hi> but let them look to that, to remove the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples they have made, or to bear the guilt of them.</p>
            <p>The ſum of his next objection is this: that Baptiſm it ſelf <hi>obliges the perſon baptized to confeſs the faith of Chriſt crucified,</hi> and exhibits vertue and power to that purpoſe, and therefore thoſe words <hi>in token,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be more properly and immediately after Baptiſm, and not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62754:10"/> ſigning with the ſign of the Croſs, <hi>as if baptizing with water were not ſufficient of it ſelf, but more over the ſign of the Croſs needful to bind the Conſcience and confer the bleſſing—which is too too like a Sacrament upon a Sacrament:</hi> where we may obſerve the ſlineſs of this Author, who would fain inſinuate a charge, which he dares not own: This adding the ſign of the Croſs to Baptiſm is, <hi>as if baptizing with water were not ſufficient of it ſelf, and is too too like a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament upon a Sacrament:</hi> Speak out man, is it ſo, or not? does the Church of <hi>England</hi> make the ſign of the Croſs eſſential to Baptiſm, and that Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm is imperfect without it? here his courage fails him, as not daring to aſſert ſo known a falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: the Church of <hi>England</hi> having ſo expreſly declared the contrary in the XXXVI. Canon, and in her Rubrick after the Office for private Baptiſm, where the Child privately baptized without the ſign of the Croſs, is declared to be <hi>lawfully and ſufficiently bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and ought not to be baptized again:</hi> The ſum then of his argument is this, that he dares not approve the ſign of the Croſs, becauſe the uſe of it after Baptiſm may by a perverſe interpretation ſeem to be what it is not, and what he dares not affirm it to be.</p>
            <p>It is ſome comfort, that this Writer acknowledges in the next Paragraph, that the Primitive Chriſtians did uſe the ſign of the Croſs, as indeed they did, both in adminiſtring Baptiſm, and upon divers other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which one would think, might juſtifie the Church of <hi>England</hi> in conforming to a Primitive pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; but what he adds, that they did it <hi>to diſtinguiſh themſelves from the Pagans, who ſcorned the Croſs, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with every ſign and token of it;</hi> is never al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as the reaſon of this practice by the ancient Chriſtians, who did not uſe this ſign to diſtinguiſh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62754:10"/> themſelves from <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> (though every pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar uſage, for what reaſon ſoever it be taken up, will neceſſarily prove a note of diſtinction) but to declare, that as much as a crucified Chriſt was ſcorned both by <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> they were not aſhamed of the croſs, but did put their whole truſt and confidence in their crucified Lord, and were ready, when ever God plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call them to it, to be conformed to their ſuffering Head; and this is a perpetual reaſon for this uſe, while the Church has any enemies, and it is never like to be without, while there are either Atheiſts, or Fanaticks, or Papiſts. That the ſign of the croſs has been abuſed by Papiſts to idolatrous purpoſes, is no better argument againſt uſing the ſign of the croſs, than it is againſt own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the croſs it ſelf; for in uſing the ſign of the croſs, we only own the croſs, that is, we profeſs to own a cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Lord, and the Doctrine and Religion of the Croſs. But this Perſon is much miſtaken in the temper of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which neither does any thing, nor leaves any thing undone, meerly for a note of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſeparation; that is a piece of vanity and affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is peculiar to Phariſees, and ſome other People, who are very like them.</p>
            <p>He has one objection more againſt the order of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, which refers to the Rubrick at the end of that Office: Viz. <hi>It is certain by Gods word, that Children which are baptized, dying before they commit actual ſin, are undoubtedly ſaved.</hi> Now had I a mind to wave this diſpute, I might tell him, that we do not give our aſſent and conſent to this Rubrick, becauſe though it be <hi>contained in,</hi> yet it is not <hi>preſcribed by</hi> the Book of Common prayer, that is, it is never to be uſed, and we aſſent and conſent only to the uſe of thoſe things, which are both <hi>contained in</hi> and <hi>preſcribed by</hi> that Book: but ſince this is evidently the doctrine of our Church, as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62754:11"/> appears both from the Homilies, and ſeveral paſſages in the Office of Baptiſm it ſelf, I ſhall briefly conſider his objections againſt it.</p>
            <p>And firſt, he wiſhes <hi>they had quoted the place,</hi> where this is affirmed in Scripture; for he knows not where to find it; and I would deſire him to tell me, whether nothing be undoubtedly certain by Scripture, but what we have an expreſs Text for, if not, we muſt reject the Baptiſm of Infants too, which will put an end to the diſpute concerning their ſalvation, when bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
            <p>If thoſe who are regularly admitted into the Church of Chriſt, have a right to the bleſſings of the Covenant, then they have a title to ſalvation; if they have not, then Baptiſm is an inſignificant ceremony, and not the Seal of a Covenant, which I ſuppoſe our Author will not eaſily affirm, no, not to oppoſe the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I ſay, thoſe who are regularly admitted by baptiſm, for ſo our Church ſuppoſes, which anſwers moſt of his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and impertinent queries.</p>
            <p>If the Children of very bad Parents be regularly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by baptiſm, or to ſpeak plainer, may be lawfully baptized, as in ſome caſes no doubt they may, we muſt acknowledge they receive the benefit of baptiſm too; but if any are baptized, who have no right to baptiſm, we are not bound to prove, that baptiſm ſhall be of any advantage to them: no more than that a Child ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit an Eſtate by vertue of an illegal or fraudulent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance.</p>
            <p>Thus the ſuppoſition of a Chriſtian King baptizing the Children of <hi>Pagans, Turks, Jews,</hi> by the ſame force by which he conquered their Parents, concerns more the legality of the Act, than the vertue of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for where-ever the Sacrament is lawfully admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, it will have its due effect.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62754:11"/>
            <p>It is a very pretty objection againſt the vertue of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, that it ſuppoſes it to be <hi>in the power of a man to make Infants ſure and certain of ſalvation;</hi> viz. by mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of them, as ſoon as they are baptized, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, he teaches Whores a more charitable way of murdering their Infants, to baptize them firſt, that ſo their Souls may be ſaved, which is true Fanatick talk, and proves the objector to have more need of good Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, than a ſerious anſwer; for let him put the caſe, as odly, as he pleaſes; Children that are lawfully bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, are in Covenant with God, and have a good title to ſalvation, and thoſe, who murder them ſend them to Heaven, as other Murderers do all the good men they kill. He asks juſt ſuch another raving que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; <hi>May a Miniſter, ſince baptizing gives ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable title to Heaven, deny or ſuſpend the ordinance to any Infant whatſoever, if he might be permitted to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter it?</hi> if by permiſſion, he means a legal permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, according to the terms and conditions of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, the anſwer is plain, that he ought not to deny it, that is, a Goſpel Miniſter ought not to deny Baptiſm to any Infant, who has a juſt right to it; if he means any other permiſſion than this, the Man is mad, and needs no other anſwer; for we don't ſuppoſe, that Baptiſm works like a ſpell or charm to whomſoever it be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, but its vertue depends upon a Divine inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore requires perſons duly qualified to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it.</p>
            <p>But he ſtrangely aggravates the cruelty of thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who refuſe to baptize Children, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keep them under a ſuſpicion of damnation, becauſe their Parents <hi>ſcruple God-fathers and God-mothers, and the ſign of the Croſs,</hi> ſuch an one, he ſays, <hi>deſerves if poſſible to be unchriſtened himſelf again, and turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Canibals, as one more deeply dipt, and baptized in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62754:12"/> their barbarous inhumanities;</hi> and adds, <hi>and yet if he be a true Son of the Church, and punctually obſerve his preſcribed rule, he muſt not baptize any Infant without God fathers and God-mothers, without ſigning it with the ſign of the Croſs, whether it be ſaved or damned;</hi> ought not this Man of conſcience, nay of a tender conſcience, to have been very ſure this charge had been juſt, before he had condemned the whole Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be <hi>turned among Canibals?</hi> and yet nothing can be more palpably falſe, for the Church of <hi>England</hi> has expreſly ordered her Miniſters, as is plain in the form of private Baptiſm, to baptize Children without God-fathers and God-mothers, or the ſign of the croſs, where there is any apparent danger of death, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be the Parents fault, how ſcrupulous ſoever he be, not the Miniſters, if his Child die unbaptized. I know not what remark to make on this, but ſhall leave it to himſelf, and every impartial Reader to think on it.</p>
            <p>But yet, I muſt farther obſerve, that to aſſert the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of baptized Infants, does not deny ſalvation to all that are unbaptized, though we are not ſo certain from the Word of God of the ſalvation of the one, as of the other: the ſalvation of baptized Infants depends on an expreſs Covenant, but we have the goodneſs and clemency of the divine nature, as a reaſon to hope well of others, eſpecially of the Children of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who were born within the Pale of the Church, and were deſigned by their Parents to be made the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible members of it.</p>
            <p>Nor is the denial of Chriſtian burial to ſuch Infants as die unbaptized any argument, (as he ſuggeſts) that our Church doubts of their ſalvation, but only, that ſhe does not own them as actual members of the Church, as no Perſons are, who are not actually admitted into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62754:12"/> the Chriſtian Church by Baptiſm: and poſſibly this may be deſigned as an act of Diſcipline to correct the neglect of Parents, and to beget in them a greater ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for the Chriſtian Sacraments.</p>
            <p>His laſt objection is againſt the office for the burial of the Dead: in which we find theſe words, <hi>for aſmuch as it hath pleaſed God of his great mercy to take unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Soul of our dear Brother here departed,</hi> &amp;c. where taking them to <hi>himſelf,</hi> he ſays, muſt ſignifie taking them <hi>into Heaven, if we believe the Lords Prayer, Our Father, which art in Heaven;</hi> but is God no where elſe then, but in Heaven, becauſe he is there in an <hi>eminent manner?</hi> does not the wiſe man tell us, that <hi>the ſpirits of men departed, return unto God, who gave them, Eccl.</hi> 12. 7. Does that ſignifie going into heaven? then we have Scripture for it, that all men are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for the Spirits of all Men after death return to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To return to God,</hi> and to be <hi>taken to him,</hi> ſignifies <note place="margin">Falkners libertas Eccl. ch. 5. ſ. 9.</note> to be put into the immediate diſpoſal of God, which as a Learned man well obſerves, <q rend="inline">Our Church ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth to be an act of mercy in God, through the grace of Chriſt, <hi>who hath the Keys of Hell and Death;</hi> that dying perſons do not forthwith go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the power of the Devil, who had the <hi>power of Death, Heb. 2. 14.</hi> but do immediately go into the hands of the great God, and our Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to be diſpoſed of by him according to the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and conditions of the Goſpel-Covenant, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the ſenſe of the ancient Church, which in the Offices of Burial, magnified the divine power, whereby the unjuſt and Tyrannous power of the Devil was overcome, and our Lord receiveth us, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to his peculiar and moſt righteous judgment.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62754:13"/>
            <p>But ſtill he urges that other expreſſion, that <hi>we commit his body to the ground, in ſure and certain hope of the Reſurrection to eternal life, which words</hi> (he tells us) <hi>muſt neceſſarily be ſpoken with reference to the perſon, then interred, inaſmuch as they are the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the foregoing declaration,</hi> viz. <hi>God's taking his Soul to himſelf. Committing his Body to the ground,</hi> muſt indeed neceſſarily refer to the perſon interred, but there is no neceſſity every thing that follows ſhould, for it is not <hi>his,</hi> but <hi>the</hi> Reſurrection to life, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our hope of, our Church thinking it fit on ſuch a ſad occaſion as this, to declare their hope of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Reſurrection; and ſince <hi>God's taking his Soul to himſelf,</hi> does not neceſſarily infer the ſalvation of ſuch a perſon, as I have already ſhewed, we cannot thence infer that the Reſurrection to life refers to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red perſon neither.</p>
            <p>But he has found one paſſage, which he ſays, <hi>puts it out of all doubt,</hi> (that when we bury a <hi>known Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, Fornicator, Drunkard, we declare and avouch that his ſoul is aſſuredly gone to Heaven</hi>) viz. that in the prayer after burial, <hi>that when we ſhall depart this life we may reſt</hi> in him, (viz. <hi>in Chriſt) as our hope is, this our Brother doth:</hi> this I grant refers to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred perſon, but is no argument, that the former expreſſions do, for this is only a judgment of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which differs much from <hi>a ſure and certain hope.</hi> There are various degrees of hope, and ſome of them ſo little, that we can hardly deny them to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though never ſo wicked; for where we are not abſolutely ſure, that they died wholly impenitent, we have ſome degree of hope, and though we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear this of too too many, yet we are ſeldom ſo certain of it, as to exclude all hopes of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62754:13"/>
            <p>But as a fuller juſtification of our Church in this matter, we may conſider, that this Office of Burial ſuppoſes, that the Perſon interred died in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church; and were Church-cenſures duly adminiſtred, as this Office preſumes them to be and as certainly they would be, were not the Church weakned by powerful Schiſms and Factions, no Man could die in the Communion of the Church, but ſuch as we ſhould have very good reaſon in the judgment of charity to hope well of; and ſince, through the decay of Diſcipline, many die in the Communion of the Church, who deſerved excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, I doubt not, but who-ever ſhall leave out that ſentence, <hi>as our hope is, this our Brother doth,</hi> at the Burial of ſome notorious profligate ſinners, complies with the intention of the Church, and may juſtifie himſelf to his Superiours for doing ſo.</p>
            <p>Having thus examined, and, as I think, anſwered this Miniſter's objections againſt Conformity, I muſt now look back, and take notice of the only piece of ingenuity he has been guilty of throughout this Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet; and that is, where he owns the lawful uſe of an <hi>eſtabliſhed Liturgy, or preſcribed form of publick prayers;</hi> nay, that as he <hi>ſays nothing againſt a Liturgy, or preſcribed form of publick prayers in the general, ſo neither againſt the main doctrine contained in the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of this Book of Common-prayers in particular:</hi> and in requital of this, I ſhall as readily acknowledge what he adds, that <hi>it is quite another thing to be bound up to declare my unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained in the Book,</hi> (but he ought alſo to have added, and <hi>preſcribed by the Book) together with thoſe prayers:</hi> that is, that there is a real diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between that conformity, which is required of a Clergy-man, and that which is required of a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:</p>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
